[SPEAKER_00]: One can pervade the body with rapture, because it's very, very even faster.
[SPEAKER_00]: The important thing is to know that it's on the level of intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's on the level of your mind, not on the level of
[SPEAKER_01]: Observation of physical sensations, or body sweeping, or whatever else people might do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, all of those little things that you're kind of trying to patch up, they're all implying this intention of safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're not seeing the intention to pervade your body with rapture, none of these things can actually bring any understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's that's the important thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to develop understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to just keep having to go through body sweeping, attention, relaxing, relaxation technique, shavasanas, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, that's all... well, it's aiming at the wrong thing, and that wrong thing might sometimes imply the correct intention, but you don't even know what correct intention is, which means you won't discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, purveying your body with rapture, or relaxing your body, it's done to the body as a unit, as a whole, through that general intention of relaxing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can even relax yourself by trying to understand what the relaxing is, as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as I say, relaxing, relax... What is relaxing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if somebody tells me to relax, and I want to relax, what would... what do I think?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the attitude that I have?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that attitude, basically, it's an attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, words, from attitude of the mind in regard to the body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just, as I said before, toward your elbows or shoulders or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's all you can say.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that, all of that, all of the other things people, people don't account for, it's just because they don't really know where to look.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, all these things might sometimes induce the the genuine relaxing, the genuine rapture.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they don't know why or how, which means it's not understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they just stumble upon it when it comes, and they don't, they wouldn't know how to do it again.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, when people say, oh, in the suttas, oh, I have taken jhānas at will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's done through understanding, through full understanding of jhānas up, and then you just say, yes, you know, but they don't come by chance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, jhānas is a particular attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Particular establishment of mind in regard for bhagavad-gītā.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you keep refining that, but it's the same, it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you've got to be able to notice that general attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever it is, you want relaxation at some point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've got to be able to, oh, I know how to relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will know how to relax by trying to find out how to relax.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, find out in terms of discerning the nature of what an intention to relax is at a time, not just by reading about some, you know, I don't know, relaxation self-help books and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I tell you, just listen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you just relax now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just sit and relax.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can kind of let it sort of go quickly, whatever, but if you stop and think about it, what would you do?
[SPEAKER_01]: What would you intend?
[SPEAKER_01]: What kind of attitude would you arouse in regard to your present situation that is sort of rooted in your body?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to relax, if you want to relax.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could describe it in different ways, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could say, uppervailing with rapture, or you can say, like, what the Ānāpānasati Siddha says, calming down the bodily determinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the bodily saṅkharas, basically, things upon which... sorry, bodily things upon which other things depend.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't, again,
[SPEAKER_01]: Sankaras are always plural in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you can do is recognize that plurality as a single phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your body as a whole has all sorts of manifestations, all sorts of intentionality that pertains to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you do basically is, ah, you count that whole down and all of these particular things are counted as a result.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have the intention of counting down your body on that general level,
[SPEAKER_01]: On a mental level, then, whatever you do with that body cannot be not caught, if you're genuinely caught.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, usually, I would think, yeah, you calm down your breath, you make the breaths lighter or slower, and then that will affect your body, that's gonna affect your muscles, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, so you try to mess around in a particular
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, chasing this, there might result in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But basically, sometimes people say, yeah, but it helps me or... And the only reason it helps is because at the time, that particular thing they're trying to come down, stands for the experience as a body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're so concerned over, you know, I don't know, some particular aspect of your body that's worrying you, or that is extremely not calm, or whatever else, then, yeah, calming that down would stand for calming down the whole body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because basically, at that time, that particular aspect of the body stands for that which body is, in your experience, as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why people who do have that view and do that, they can't do it at will.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can only do it when it happens that the particular aspect they're focusing on stands for the body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that won't always be the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes there won't be any particular aspect and then it will be just kind of generic collection of particular aspects that stand for the single phenomenon of the body in this experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the person wants to practice calming down the body, as a meditation, basically, well, initially, the most important thing would be to not allow himself, herself, to descend onto, like, particular aspects of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just stay with the mental thought of
[SPEAKER_01]: Counting down the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, that's all it... it doesn't... you don't need more than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Counting down the body results in calmness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, obviously, the mind needs more, wants more.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't need more, but wants more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wants to say words.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wants to designate it in the in the terms that it's used to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those terms are not subtle enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: to designate the phenomenon of counting down the body as a phenomenon, as a general phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just not subtle enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said before, instead of then coursing up, so to speak, how the body feels and trying to pin it down and go into sensations or whatever else, you should actually define those designations you're trying to designate that gen... general feeling... sorry, general phenomenon of the body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: It begins to sound abstract, but that's, you know, whenever you read, like in the suttas, when the Buddha was speaking about meditation and perception of light or this, yeah, people lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't... it's hard to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in this particular instance, basically, all you have to do is just remember that you have no choice but have your body right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, okay, learn how to relax without ending up
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking particular things, particular aspects about the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just think about calm down.
[SPEAKER_01]: What does that mean, as a phenomenon?
[SPEAKER_01]: Calming down.
[SPEAKER_01]: How is that done?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even specifically in regard to body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just I tell you, as an external person, as an other to you, I tell you, I utter a designation, calm down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you do have
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a degree of meaning in regard to that designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might not correspond 100% to what I regard calming down is, but certainly enough that we are able to talk and discuss it and communicate to an extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: For yourself, then, you can take up that designation, calm down, and see how far you can take it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without, you know, falling into some psychological explanations and things that kind of... No, no, it is this, or it might be that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just for you, in your own terms, without resorting to anything external, an act of calming down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you do it anytime?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you do it in regard to anything?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it, basically?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you discern?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you see?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I think it would be a mistake if I start imagining
[SPEAKER_01]: That's again, that's like, basically, trying to induce the calmness, doing things that you think might actually result in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they sometimes might, but not for the reasons you think they would.
[SPEAKER_00]: But an image of, say, an image might arise in the mind due to the fact that I have the intention to calm, like I might have a...
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, because your concern is not in regard to that image, but it's in regard to intention, to come, then those images become secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, things like, you're just talking about the itch or, let's say, there's like anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you overcome with anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your body is already in a state of shaking or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not shouting, but just this anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, intention to non-anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to have... you need to establish that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's quite...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite difficult at that stage.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean... Well, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, the only reason you were able to... well, the only reason one was able to get so angry in a state of, you know, being shaken by anger and so on, is because the intention of non-anger hasn't really been developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, at that time, all you need to do is just greet your
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when you're not that angry, practice the intention of non-anger, and practice the intention of dispelling the, you know, kind of looming anger, or looming bad mood, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, seeing it at its very early stages, so to speak, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Discerning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, training in regards to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it will never come to that fully-blown anger, where you're like... you don't know what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The resistance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It starts with resistance, starts with aversion, and then you just...
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't look at it, you ignore it, you turn a blind eye, you give in to it, because it's... oh, well, it's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not as angry, so it's okay, and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then it ends up being accumulated, and then eventually you get very angry over nothing, over some silly things.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just become kind of an excuse to let the whole thing out.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're always aware, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: People can never be like, completely, oh, yeah, I was so angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: You always know what you're doing, because anger, or the same with lust, you know, as powerful as they can get, they're always rooted in bad faith, which means you always know what you're doing, but you're covering it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just not recognizing that you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you refuse, basically, to just... you even refuse to... yeah, you refuse to look at the fact that you know what you're doing, and then you just let that built-up anger or built-up lust go.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, it's mindfulness, in a way, like knowing that you are aware of something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Admitting to yourself, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeds authentic attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Attitude of not... it's basically attitude of non-self-deception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, another thing, maybe, is probably useful to mention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Back onto meditation, if you just practice the intention of calming down the body, in general, or relaxing, or whatever you want to call it, it's important to know that then, yeah, you might start feeling your body differently.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, you've been you've been cultivated the intention of calming down your body, you might just
[SPEAKER_01]: You start feeling whatever, light or or or just, well, it's like, oh, I don't feel my body anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all relative to your day-to-day life, how you're used to feeling your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not actually any accomplishment in itself, to, like, feel your body, I don't know, like light, cloud or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all a novelty, just in regard to how you're used to feeling your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all fine, as long as you don't then become sort of too concerned, too obsessed, too keen on having your body felt like that all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's again falling down onto particular and forgetting that it was a bad intention to just calm down the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, what that intention results in, it's all secondary and you do not care about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes you can be very calm and your body will feel very normal.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't feel any like, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, tingling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tingling sensation.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know, but basically how people...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know how people would describe it, but you know what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you relax your body and then... Well, you might be struggling for words to describe it, because it becomes different to how you used to, kind of, perceive your body in your day-to-day life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no matter how ambiguously you might be perceiving your body at the time, as a result of that calming down, that's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was never the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: The goal is not to actually feel and perceive these certain ways the body can be felt or perceived.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about recognizing, discerning and cultivating intention to calm down the phenomenon of body, to calm down the nature of body.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, when you're doing this, practicing these kinds of intentions, and then seeing
[SPEAKER_00]: See, noticing the result of these intentions, so far, an actual calm body, whatever particular thing's happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can get a bit green.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well... No, well... Yeah, I mean...
[SPEAKER_00]: But I always start to think about...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I have to think about the principle that's happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That just determines this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And without this, this wouldn't... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...be hap... You know, the other particular thing's going to be hap...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically just another step.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a course of developing your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start developing your mind in regard to recognize the intention to calm down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Calming down the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, the pleasant results as a result of that... Now, you have to train your mind in regard to them, because now they're pulling you a bit too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you want to always have that calm body and never... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That calm body wasn't yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: The intention was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, even the intention wasn't yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that intention would be...
[SPEAKER_01]: Indiscernible?
[SPEAKER_00]: Indiscernible.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if that is a word, but it would be impossible to discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: That intention would be impossible to discern if that body was not already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that body pertains...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, because that intention pertains to that body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every intention is mental, but because it pertains to the body, in its nature, in regards to the body, it's a bodily intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: But every intention manifests on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a bodily intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the body has a possibility to be calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: So all you're doing, you're attending possibility of calm in regard to body, and that's a bodily intention of calming down.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are... there is no subject there that it's actually producing that intention towards this external body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, that which is the subject producing the intention in regards to the external body, that subject also belongs to that external body through that intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's not really a subject.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's the the calmness of the body, the intention to calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all in regards to the body and the nature of the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that subject that inevitably appears for kutujana in regards to the body,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a counterpart, a negative sort of phenomenon regarding the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't have to worry about it in terms of trying to abolish it or remove it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You actually have to acknowledge it and then stop regarding it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all you take.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by not regarding it as yours, that subject will cease to be the center of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just becomes an individual arising and ceasing in the same way pañca-khandhā arises and ceases until they completely break apart in parinibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What about awareness that's there?
[SPEAKER_00]: There's attention being paid to certain things, like recognizing the... Well, the awareness in itself, you can't discern that.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no such thing as pure awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, like, the thing is, you can say, oh, pure awareness, but you fail to see that your designation, the very words you used as pure awareness, stand for the matter in regard to which you're aware.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, there is no pure awareness as such, because if there were, well, you wouldn't be able to utter it, you wouldn't be able to discern it, and in that way, it means it can't be.
[SPEAKER_00]: I would say there is the noticing of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Also present with
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can discern that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't, in the same sense that Buddha said, you can't separate feelings, perception and intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're conjoined, they're not disjoined, it all comes one.
[SPEAKER_01]: An examiner...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's all I'm pointing out, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can say there's awareness in regard to it and there is noticing of it, but just make sure you don't mystify it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't become an entity in itself of pure noticing, pure awareness, pristine awareness, or all sorts of terms you might end up using.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to see it in the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to discern, because it's always in the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is always in the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just have to actually find it in context.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the context that it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you might recognize it in the context once or twice, and then you develop a view that this thing is always in the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you put the context over the actually already arisen context.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if that is the same context, the fact that you are putting it over means you're assuming it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the wrong thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're assuming it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eventually, you want to stop assuming any context and just be discerning the arisen context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, by knowing that that context is always there, you know, ah, it's just a question of time of me discerning it, if that's how you look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can discern it by learning how to, well, see it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by writing it with your own terms, but actually reading it
[SPEAKER_01]: The way it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in order to read it, you know, you have to know how, you know, to know how it's written, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to learn that language.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that language is nothing other than what I said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just basically training your mind in, well, in becoming subtler than the designation that you used to, well, used to have, used to entertain in regard to these things that will pertain to the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example, many people
[SPEAKER_01]: wouldn't say that their thoughts exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because for them, they're used to.
[SPEAKER_01]: For them, the measure of existence is what they're so used to, so entrenched in, that they get through senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, their thoughts are just these
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I mean, but they fail to see that it's a little bit of a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because just by saying, oh, my thoughts don't really exist, you were designating that very thing, that then you deny to be existing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because for you, bhāva, existence, has been, like, quite, sort of, charged up, brought up, far out, whereby now pertains to the just senses and the palpable aspects of your five senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how bhāva grows, bhāva accumulates.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a static thing, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bhāva-bhāva.
[SPEAKER_01]: Existence-existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for some people, things can exist more.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they have more significance, if they have more weight, if there is more lust and aversion and delusion in regard to it, they proliferate.
[SPEAKER_01]: They accumulate.
[SPEAKER_01]: They get heavier.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's hard to stop you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you stop by recognizing that, oh, hold on, if my thoughts don't exist, how can I even think about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they exist, just much subtler than things that you might grab with your hand or see with your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you start recognizing what's in common then?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is in common to things that I can see with my eyes, things I can grab with my hand, and things I can think about?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's... what is in common is that they actually, all of them, are thought of.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're all mental images.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're all dhammas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already got the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of things is to appear as an image, to arise on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you recognize, yeah, that is what comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the fact that I'm holding it in my hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm only able to hold this thing in my hand, is because there was already a mental image of a hand, things to be held, a sense, a sense, sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that was already manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the senses will not operate.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mind is not, you know, the reign, sort of, if the mind is not in control of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, the mind is not in control, because people don't practice restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they do meet in mind, and mind has a final end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's say, mind comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then it just comes down to repetition of that recognition of what these dhammas are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, this is...
[SPEAKER_01]: An object, but again, the ego, you designate it as an object, which is a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: That whole designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everything becomes recognized, because everything already is a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: A mental image that pertains to senses, a mental image that pertains to a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more you practice that, the more your mind withdraws from the threshold of being that was set far out in the in the sense world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you recognize... it just... it just fades away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now the mind recognizes more, greater nature of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, what about this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, dharma is ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's when the mind ceases to be established upon anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you do have things arising and ceasing, but they don't really exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because existence, bhāva, is that significance, charged with that significance of mind, form, significance of lust, aversion or delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you remove that, and then you can say you just have mere arising and mere ceasing, but they don't exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's again...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, well, that's what I wrote about in that article, in that essay, Appearance is an Existence, for Putrajana.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, basically, let's say like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have existence without appearance, but you can have appearance without existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, most of people who are far down
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, at the end of existence, when they look back, all they see is existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for them, appearance, existence is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you actually start walking up, reversing that thing, there will be a point where you went across, and then it goes, no, things appear, and they don't exist anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of no weight, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're drained, dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, with a root cut off, like a palm stump.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the palm stump is still there, appearing, but it's dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not charged anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not proliferating anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it doesn't induce feelings anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't... it cannot be the cause of suffering anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cut up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even that will break apart eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: For another time, even the appearance breaks apart when the ideas break apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it doesn't... that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't re-emerge.
[SPEAKER_01]: For that very reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: You re-emerged because of that charge in regard to appearance remaining.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even at the time of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you remove the significance of mind, the personality, the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those things come from that very same charge of existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Weight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Weight to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, you can actually, you can arrive at that by just what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say, sure, everything exists.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means everything... well, everything affects you in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything has a certain significance to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you take yourself to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of that existence, what does it have in common then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Existence of the sense objects, of the senses, of the sense pleasures, existence of the thoughts, abstract thoughts, imaginary thoughts,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what it has in common is, it appears as a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah, that mental image is affected with a parasite that kind of makes you think it's for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I must be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, you can undo that only once you first acknowledge it as a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that mental image is not in your head.
[SPEAKER_01]: That mental image is right there where the things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the distance, say, looking at the other side of the valley, on that hill over there,
[SPEAKER_01]: Mental image is right there, there, out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, saying out there, that's another mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole space, it's a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the sense...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's probably not the best way to call a mental image, because for most of the people it would imply, ah, it's all in my head.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it would be like a form of idealism, saying it's all in my... it's all in my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind is not yours to begin with, which means your mind is out there with things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you are not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can just say an image, or you can just say a dhamma, or a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, thought already has connotation for many people, as opposed to the senses, or this is the real world, and then this is the world of my thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But whether it's a thought, whether it's the, in verse of karma, real world, what they have in common, they have in common to appear as an image.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, obviously, for Europeans saying phenomenon, ah, it's just philosophy.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just some weird philosophy we've done, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Call it whatever you want, but phenomenon would be the most... well, it would be the most accurate, actually, designation for it to appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a nature to appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything has a nature to appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the most abstract, ambiguous, impossible-to-define thoughts, they appear as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, when you start discerning the appearance within existence, existence would become redundant, eventually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything becomes equal, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: In an emotional sense, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing is wiped out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's why arahant is always at peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Immovable.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, there are inherent significances, you know, that still stays.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, you wouldn't start using, you know, a cup to sweet the leaves, because that's not significance of the cup.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of these significances would be implying... would... well, sorry, would contain any more any emotional significance of my cup, my dear cup, or my lovely broom.
[SPEAKER_01]: I really like this broom, it's really practical or...
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't be for you, it won't be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it would be a cup for drinking, broom for sweeping.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, if you want to mess about, you can try sweeping leaves with a cup, but it would be ridiculous and it wouldn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then again, it would be an intention to try something ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that wouldn't be for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, you would not be affected by any of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you certainly wouldn't be able to feel any suffering or pressure of any feeling in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't mean your mind becomes blank or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, everything stays the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just don't feel anything in regard to it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't mean that you negate or destroy or ignore significance of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why arahants were not recognized by ordinary people.
[SPEAKER_01]: External.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes they look worse, their behavior or things they would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, since we're talking about existence, bhārata-bhāva, and it's, eh... but you're just saying, eh... assumption determines bhārata-bhāva.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's, that's the ultimate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not... Yeah, based on, on the, on the extent of your assumption, that's how bhārata-bhāva will be established.
[SPEAKER_00]: The assumption being,
[SPEAKER_01]: In your assumption?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is... not seeing it as... as it appears, first of all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, assumption is basically... you take it to be something, without actually knowing whether that is that... what you take it to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I said, like, assuming a context, what you said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a context of... of... of... when there is an experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you can also assume the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Often there is an experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for you at the time, because you assume it, it is the real context.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't correspond to the actual context of the arisen experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because all you have is your assumption of that context, it is what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why once you undo upādāna, the assumption, you can't arise again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can only arise
[SPEAKER_01]: When you don't really... when you take things at face value, when you don't really know if it is like that or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you know that it is like that or not, you can't then...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, now I'll assume that it is this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically an assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like taking a stand in regard to anything, without actually knowing whether that stand is right or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that goes to very subtle levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you assume an assumption, you've got to sense it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the fundamental assumption that things are for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That things are yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't have to worry about trying to chase this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just start with that fundamental assumption and it will undo all of the other assumptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Assumptions of sensuality and views and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Assumption of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, and you can actually ask that to anybody.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so what is that you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where are you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Who are you?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you wouldn't...
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, there is a very strong notion of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that notion is real, because that assumption of for me has been never questioned, never challenged, never discerned.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you did really develop a sense of me, based on constantly assuming that things are for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just stop assuming that things are for you, and then the assumption of me will fade, because you won't be feeling it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: What about this, eh... you know, when people ask you, what is myself?
[SPEAKER_00]: And it says, you know, why are questions about self and the world unanswerable?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the question you just asked, why... because it implies that there is actually something that is yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say, what is my self?
[SPEAKER_01]: It means, yeah, so we both agree that there is your self and now you're just asking me what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's a wrong question because we don't agree that there is your self.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't agree.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you ask me that question, I'm not going to answer it in a way that would just sort of make you think you were right to ask it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you were not right to ask it in the first place because that question assumes the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a sense of self?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I wrong in thinking that I am?
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't ask that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You ask, what is myself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you already take for granted that it's yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now you just need to know what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is kind of funny, because it's like you really know what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha would be silent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or reply in a, well, seemingly unrelated manner, saying, describing patitsaṁpāda, describing the
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, independent origination.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were to see that, again, things arise on their own, they manifest, the nature is to be manifest, and you're not saying that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything, be it your senses, your thoughts, you already find there all you can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can intend on top of it, you can, you know, you can pursue it, you can build your whole life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, fundamentally, your senses and things in regard to your senses, they're just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just use them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you certainly have no access to, nor even a view into, where they came from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even just asking where, even the assumption that they came from somewhere, doesn't even... even that doesn't apply to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just given, and then they go.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you die, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just recognizing that, that they're inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you can do is, like, secondarily use them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means they can't really be yours, because if it's yours, you would have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's often in the city like a borrowed or a gold or jewelry.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's gonna be, and you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, everybody knows they'll die.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody knows the senses will fall apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you still go ahead, use it as if it belongs to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you have to do is remove that sense of belonging in regard to things that you're using.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what are the things that you're using?
[SPEAKER_01]: Your eyes, your nose, your ears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind, basically, all of the senses and your mind...
[SPEAKER_01]: There was in that sutra, when they... when the Buddha said, it's because people take that which belongs to Mara, Mara does what he wants with them, on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the things that belong to Mara?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's eyes and forms, ears and sounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, it's pretty much nothing else in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everything belongs to Mara.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the problem is not you using it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can use it warily, like the the the the Veda Sutta, the Dhyana Sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is you appropriating it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You taking it to be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're appropriately using, not the actually doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, through using, you end up appropriating it, because you're using it unwarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how does this using work?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because there's the intention to do something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, using works by doing it, without taking it to be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you cut things up, when you slice them apart, separate, there's an intention to use them, to attempt to something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so on and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's no
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no stationary position around us.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am the self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, now I'll use my intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll use my body.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, there is no stationary position.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, because people do regard their intentions as yours, as theirs, as belonging to them, they generate.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result of that, there is a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a sense of center.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a sense of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can then appropriate that center as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might kind of pull out from all of these particular things, and you cannot mind, like, putrajana can be free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You let go of that, but still hold on to their self-view, sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their center, you could say, in its rightful... what you can call it, rightfully, is a good person.
[SPEAKER_00]: What about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you can call the center, not the... Well, no, that's how you can call the appropriated center.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop regarding that center... You start seeing that center as depending upon things that are centered around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't be your center anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said, was it King Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't remember the name.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, well, would the king, a king, would a king be determined as a king without his king's possessions, without his castle, without his queen, without his appointment, without all these things, without his ownership of, you know, the great armies?
[SPEAKER_01]: He wouldn't be a king.
[SPEAKER_01]: He might call himself a king.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he's delusional, he won't be a king.
[SPEAKER_01]: If nobody ever appointed him, he's not born in a family that appoints himself as king and then their offspring is king, that he appropriates externally, I'm the king, he wouldn't be a king.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of these possessions, the title, everything else, are things that determine that center of me as a king.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you then start seeing all of these things that you're taking to be yours, as not yours, then you will fade.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not I am, therefore things are mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because I take things to be mine, therefore I end up being.
[SPEAKER_01]: But a center remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the center remains in a sense, but again, in the same sense, you can say appearance remains, but existence ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's only known once existence ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you let go of that center, you can say... you can see what sort of center remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it can be a very different sense of center than to a sense of center that Putujan is used to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or not very different, if he was a very wise and restrained Putujanā, and then he just needed... he had a little dust in his eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends how far off-center have you established your Putujana center.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about coming back to the center.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cool.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, if all of this being, existence, phenomena, it's sort of feeling too much,
[SPEAKER_01]: Just restart.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the first step is, why do you want to practice at all?
[SPEAKER_01]: To be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can just revolve around that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because becoming free from suffering frees you from sense of self, frees you from existence, frees you from all of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just different approaches for different people, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some need to come from this angle, the others from that angle.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it's just, you know, if it's... if you just can't help but have it, oh, this is all abstract, I just can't get my head around it, you might not necessarily have to, but you would have to get your head around something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe not on the same intellectual level, because not all people have the same faculties, but certainly, there is no question of, oh, can I get this done with less effort?
[SPEAKER_01]: The same amount of effort needs to be, well, virtually the same, not completely the same, but almost the same amount of effort needs to be put in by every pūtūjana, just in regard to different things or a different approach.
[SPEAKER_01]: The effort of repetition, the effort of drilling, the effort of endurance, the effort of restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, it's all done for the same goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being free from suffering, being free from possibility to suffer, which is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, my being, my sense of self, my center...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: To be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understand the four noble truths and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you start discerning all the other things that Buddha was talking about within that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh!
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to look left and right from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do you suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: To what extent?
[SPEAKER_01]: When does disagreeable become suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is disagreeable suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you have disagreeable without actually suffering on account of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite useful questions to contemplate on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because most people, disagreeable, in the same sense, again, there you go, I just said, it's all the same, the rewards are on the same principles.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, I said, you can have appearance without existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't have existence without appearance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can have disagreeable without suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't have suffering without disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have suffering without disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't suffer if there's nothing disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can have disagreeable without suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and it's because you can't suffer without a disagreeable experience, that's why people by default assume, ah, removing disagreeable means removing suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that is overstepping it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is going into the domain that doesn't belong to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The domain of agreeable and disagreeable, things that just arise as agreeable and disagreeable, that's not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering in regard to it is yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's your attitude in regards to agreeable or disagreeable that's making you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever there is disagreeable, you suffer because of your attitude in regard to disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, it's the middle way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the middle way because you don't go and just remove disagreeable altogether.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't, because you're not in control of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You never were.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't stop eyes from seeing, ears from hearing, mind from thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, most certainly, you cannot order it to only see pleasant things, and hear pleasant things, and think pleasant things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even pleasant...
[SPEAKER_01]: It can be a source of disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start thinking about more pleasant, which is, you know, not what you're currently experiencing, well, that's a disagreeable experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: You created that disagreeable discrepancy, and now you suffer and encounter it, because you lust for more.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you have is far from enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: You used to be enough, but because the mind was unrestrained, you created discrepancy upon which you got established, and now you just crave, need, depend on more.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you become very unhappy, very, very affected by suffering, in regard to very pleasant experiences.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your attitude towards disagreeable and agreeable... Yeah, is what basically makes you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that attitude is actually the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not wanting disagreeable and wanting pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Overstepping it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, changing the attitude being... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing, but first knowing that you should stop being concerned about the actual agreeable and disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't go trying to change the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, of course, if you live in the middle of the city, in a horrible environment, and you want to become an arahant, well, you have to change those circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not what I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I'm talking about is if, I don't know, somebody said something that upset you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're responsible for the upset.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not responsible for what's being said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you suffer, it's on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because suffering is present when craving is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving in regard to agreeable or disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that suffering is present when agreeable or disagreeable is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can have agreeable and disagreeable without actually suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: At all.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, somebody said something that upsets you,
[SPEAKER_01]: Default, putuginal response is to, well, either get upset and say something back that will hurt them, or, if perhaps you have a bit more restraint, then, well, let's go to them and talk, or wanting their apology.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to affect it on that external level where it came from.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, you're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're, again, as I said, you're overstepping it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're misplacing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was not the suffering to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was your attitude in regard to that which has come your way in terms of somebody saying something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the first thing you recognize is like, well, there's always going to be something disagreeable in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if I get all of the people to be on my side, to agree with me, to always sing praises of me, something else will always be disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means there's always something else is going to come your way that you're not going to like.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eventually,
[SPEAKER_01]: Aging, sickness and death.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, there is no sugar coating that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you recognize it's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, but then, again, see, oh, oh my goodness, it's all, it's all depressing now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything, everything is inevitable in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is just going to come to a horrible, disagreeable end.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could see people falling into despair, if they start thinking like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then imagine
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, imagine the extent of the Buddha's discovery.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, he managed to discern that none of that is a cause for the pain that you feel, or you might feel, or the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, imagine that, like seeing through these just layers of identical glass.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you start discerning them without any external input, without...
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't have another Buddha's guidance.
[SPEAKER_01]: He saw it from the inside, which is what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is a mirror.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, you know, that's why he's the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's easier for us now, because we have it, like, laid down, pointed out, you know, outlined by the Buddha and other arahants and so on, and the suttas, mainly, only.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you then, now you know what to look for from the inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, the whole point is basically, when you recognize, oh, wow, the freedom lies within that, right through the center of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Complete freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the problem was never disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how disagreeable it was, even if it was highway robbers sawing your limbs and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was never the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: The issue was the fact that you were touched by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you were touched by it because you were picking it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you were touching it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a hot stove, and you put a hand on it, always, and you don't know how to stop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you start blaming the stove.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you want to try to remove it, abolish the stove, but it's not yours, and you can't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's a bit simplifying it a bit, but basically, craving, as a mental aptitude, is the cause.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, simultaneously, and that's it, that's why it's patīcamo pādre, it's a simultaneous presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneous dependence.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable to have dukkha present, dukkha arisen, if there is no, at the same time, to the same extent, dhamma present, dhamma arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of dhamma, absence of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of dhamma, presence of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you have a... could you have an intention of non-breathing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you guys...
[SPEAKER_01]: But not when there is no craving, because then that intention would be craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: The intention of non-craving has to be in regard to craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when there's no craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: When there is no craving, you intending to not crave would be craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, how did you cross the shore?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by not fighting the waves, by not kind of going backwards, and by not standing still.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, at the time, you intend riding.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, don't think, which I'm sure you would and everybody would, including myself, when I first read it, that it's like you need to moment, like, catch the intention in the moment and then counter it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically recognizing the general intention and then relinquishing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can always recognize the general intention by being aware of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why suffering and freedom from suffering, that's all the Buddha teaches.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if there's presence of dukkha, you know there's craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to look for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but where is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I suffer means craving is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can I, so to speak, tune my attitude whereby amidst disagreeable, I'm not suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: At all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because I'm running away from disagreeable, not because I'm ignoring disagreeable, not because I'm psychologizing the disagreeable and explaining myself, you know, ah, it's because of my childhood or this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I don't crave in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't fear the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't lust the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you don't crave, you don't overshoot, you don't step in, you don't run away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you don't react in regard to agreeable or disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you don't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, disagreeable and agreeable, it's not set in stone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can be... can arise in different extents.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you might... you might get used to a certain level of disagreeable and that ceases to cause you pain, suffering mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then the level of disagreeable increases and then you start suffering again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just... you're not training in regard to the extent of disagreeable, which is why you don't have to go and torture yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: As some ascetics thought, they would have to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not training in regard to the extent of disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're training in regard to the nature of disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you stop feeling the nature of disagreeable, the extent becomes irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, to the point of highway rollers chopping your limbs one by one with a blunt saw.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you still won't be suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was very disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, extremely disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But mentally, you actually won't be fearing it or suffering on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, death you've overcome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you overcome death.
[SPEAKER_01]: The utmost disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I was saying before, when Kuntūjana was touched by suffering, he suffers on account of that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he can't prevent it, and he knows no escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: When sotāpanna, or an ārya, is touched by suffering, he doesn't suffer under that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, fully developed ārya, who becomes an ārahant, he's not touched even in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for sotāpanna, he can suffer, but only to a certain extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, well, he can suffer to the extent of seven little grains of sand, in comparison to the Himalayas.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, for him at the time, that would be a lot of suffering, because that's all the suffering he has.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no limit to suffering, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: People can take mountains of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if there are no mountains, just a little grain, well, it will... again, it's the suffering, it's going to feel... like a little suffering will feel as much as big suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for Sarvabhāna, that little suffering will be suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if he were to remember how he used to suffer, of course, he won't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only quite a trivial matter, which is what gives even more confidence to the Buddha and the Dhamma and the practice he heard, which is why it's our confirmed confidence.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows it for himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't suffer as much as before if he will want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if he would just look then at the suffering that he still can experience, oh, yeah, there is still work to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not also the one as Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, if the circumstances are right, and they don't get challenged often, they might be quite complacent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is quite an accomplishment, getting the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, as the Buddha compared it, seven, you know, grains of sand in comparison to the Himalayas, that's how little suffering is left for somebody with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, being complacent is an unwholesome state, which means it should not be encouraged.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha never did.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, like, some of my disciples might be sotāpanna, sakadāgāmī, anāgāmī, jhāna, he'll go to them and encourage them and encourage them, arouse a sense of urgency and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is still work to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there isn't work to be done, I wouldn't be telling them to go and do the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So sotāpanna can still experience a degree of suffering in regard to disagreeable
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean he's careless, if he's not actively practicing or pursuing the Arahantship?
[SPEAKER_01]: But he knows it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't deceive himself about it, which is what Pradyumna can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: As you asked before, Pradyumna might not necessarily be experiencing suffering all the time, and that is very much the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... the Buddha said that it's because the human life, it's not solely constituted of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: People get enamored with it, intoxicated with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he does have pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If Putujan is authentic, he would recognize that, yeah, look, all these circumstances around me, my work, my family, whatever else, it's all great.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm very, very happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is going my way, for very little effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a fact.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't deny that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no, that is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, he also, if he is so aware of his pleasures, he should also be aware that that can change the next moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Misfortune, accident, anything like that, his own life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he needs to then recognize that the very foundations upon which his current happiness rests are inaccessible to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has no control over it, no say in it, can't even conceive that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, that recognition is very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even amidst all the happiness you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wouldn't recognition... it would help him?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're feeling with anxiety, and that's a very deep existential pain, suffering,
[SPEAKER_01]: And people who experience that, as the Buddha said, they have, like, you know, two outcomes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Search for the relief, and that's when it helps him, when he has enough wisdom, enough composure to go out, or just mental derangement.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, start taking pills and extreme antidepressants or whatever else, because you can't hack it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Alcohol.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or extreme distraction in terms of alcohol or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it wouldn't necessarily help him, but it's certainly the prerequisite for him seeking help.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, my experience was the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was no misfortunes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite actually comfortable, despite, you know, what what what Serbia was going through.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite a comfortable life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very good job.
[SPEAKER_01]: No problems in any department of life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But,
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognizing that any department of life can be compromised at any given second, not by you, by freak exit, by anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you cannot prevent it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is very frightening.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then again, that's the suttas when they would say, you know, young man, whatever, lame man, recognizes, I am prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't necessarily suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the suffering might be looming at the next moment, the next choice I make, the next thing I do.
[SPEAKER_01]: The result for most people is freaking out, in anxiety, losing the grip, seeking, in words and commas, medical help, chugging down the pills until they sometimes manage to forget about it and move on, cover it up enough that they're able to move on, or not, just become fully dependent, and then lose, lose their mind completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Few other people, who don't necessarily, or maybe a bit stronger mentally, for them, a recognition of that anxious sort of prospect of... things can happen, and you won't be able to prevent it, and you won't be able to not be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering is a hunter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might, you know, you might come in its crosshairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you recognize, furthermore, oh, you will come in this process, eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most people don't have to wait to get, you know, get sick and die, because, well, you're attached to plenty of other things around you.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they change, you already start suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the same nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just start recognizing, yeah, even if none of these things change, which is inconceivable,
[SPEAKER_01]: This life will come to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which means, ultimately, it will result in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'd better do something about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, recognition of that, of feeling like a prey, like a deer in a field, and you know that the hunter is there, but you can't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you can either ignore the fact that he might be there and just pretend, oh, no, this grass is very tasty and I'll just ignore it and enjoy it while I can, before the contact comes, or you'll think, no, this grass is useless to me if I'm going to end up on a hunter's table.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I might as well try and find a way out and escape it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's when, you know, young men go forth and turn out of faith and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, life can be very perfect, but recognition that that life is not in your control, just that suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's almost like everyone somehow recognizes that already.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's numb.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cover it up or you start... Cover it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't cover it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole life becomes an act of a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think I said that before, recently.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why people... that's why sensuality and sensual pursuits are not often not optional for people, in the sense that their life has been... has became a massive cover-up, that now they fully existentially depend upon sensual distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they're going to crash even harder, when the senses start to fail, and then death comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, basically, pursuing your desires and stuff, it's not like, oh, I'll do it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to, because those are the only means of you floating, not sinking down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you know, everybody knows, that every prospect, that every giving in of the desire, that every giving in towards the destruction, the core reason of covering up the fact that you're not in control of the whole thing, it's present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sankhāra-dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is... everything can be a determination for your suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sankhāra-dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: For that reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's only dukkha that arises and dukkha that ceases.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dukkha that ceases.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is only dukkha that arises and dukkha that ceases.
[SPEAKER_00]: But ceasing in dukkha is quite few.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Putujana suffers on account of his own... on account of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of being touched by suffering, he suffers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Satipaṭṭhāna knows that it's only suffering that arises and suffering that ceases, and he doesn't suffer on account of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he pursues it long enough, hard enough, he becomes an arahant, and then there won't be any suffering arising anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, as I said, you can have
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have suffering without disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can have disagreeable without suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because you are at the end of suffering, as Pratyūjana, you actually have to go through that suffering until eventually you just reach power.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is only the nuisance left on account of this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only disagreeable things, they can arise on account of the senses, but not all the suffering has been abolished.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when arahant becomes arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, any any sort of disagreeable experience that can arise, it is going to be on account of these
[SPEAKER_01]: These five aggregates, until they break apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he doesn't suffer on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when they break apart, even that disagreeable, that little annoyance of the five aggregates still arising, ceasing, will go.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for him, there's no suffering arises or suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you first recognize the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you recognize the nature of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you recognize the escape in regard to that suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize how it ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you recognize what to do in order for it to cease altogether.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you start doing it, and then you can... then you stop suffering on account of not knowing escape from arisen suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you halved it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you pursue even that further, and then even that suffering ceases, and all that it's left, it's, for another hunt, nuisance and annoyance that can arise on account of the five aggregates still... all these senses operating on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: These animals yanking left and right, but they can't pull them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, when Venerable Anuruddha...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it was also Ratapala... No, Venerable Ratapala Sutta, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he went back home and father got his, well, former wives, to dress up and try and seduce him, and kind of basically harass him, and he said that, oh, and he was a Narayan, and he was saying, oh, just stop harassing me with these sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sisters.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they fainted, because he called them sisters.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then father gave him gold.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, better throw that in the river, because you're going to be sorcerer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your graveness forge, you're holding on to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, these signs become annoying and harassing, when your eyes, the habit of the animals, the five sense animals, basically, the simile of the five senses being a respective animal, they just, you know, they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to go there.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is my feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm hungry.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't pull you, but they can still
[SPEAKER_01]: Disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can be disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Enduring the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bearing the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bearing the illness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bearing the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arahant is aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he doesn't suffer and he certainly doesn't fear it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, fear of disagreeable then prevents him to do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: He does not have that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he knows whatever disagreeable arises will cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before him, Sotāpanna knows whatever suffering on account of disagreeable arises will cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Putujanā doesn't know even that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever suffering, on account of disagreeable that arises for Putujanā, he suffers on account of that twice, on another level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's a simile of the... how was it?
[SPEAKER_01]: The two errors.
[SPEAKER_01]: Man gets hit by one error, and then he's struck by that pain, and then he gets struck by another error on account of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that doesn't happen to an ādiya-sāvaka, to a noble disciple, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's struck by one error of suffering, but he knows escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: from that pain that has arisen on account of that error.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's not struck by the second error of panic and fear and distraught.
[SPEAKER_00]: And escape is not the understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Escape is fully understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before, that's the insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why he became a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter how painful, how sufferable things arise, he won't suffer on account of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, for an hour... and then, if he pursues it fully, then they won't even arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, it will only be like disagreeable arising, agreeable arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, the Buddha says, oh, sometimes he... a person comes and asks him for the instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: He tells them what to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then they go and do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, Tathāgata is pleased.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he finds that agreeable, then another man comes and the Buddha teaches him for three more hours.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then he goes and it's completely the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, Tathāgata is displeased.
[SPEAKER_01]: He finds that disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: They said, but none of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Neither of those accounts do make the target person suffer, or get upset, or get elated with great joy, because somebody's following his instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you say, oh, this is agreeable, that's suitable, that's not suitable, that's disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's see.
[SPEAKER_00]: These terms, I don't know if we go through all of them, but the dhamma is
[SPEAKER_00]: Upanāyaka, leading to, bringing near.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leading on?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I just wrote down some translation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh, uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leading to, bringing near, leading on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's basically... you need to see it, you know, to know it, to put it simply.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you will develop the dhamma that you're trying to practice by becoming sattva and then an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by thinking you understood dhamma, but at the same time knowing that you're still putujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, understanding of the dhamma leads you onwards, further and further and further, or rather closer and closer and closer to the goal, further and further away from being putujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not like, oh, I understood the dhamma and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I keep my old ways of being putujana or whatever else, but I understood the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the dhamma then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were to gain any understanding of the dhamma, you would then recognize, oh, there is more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you get the understanding of that more and then, oh no, there is more.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is more, there is more, there is more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until the other hand says, there is no more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything has been completed.
[SPEAKER_01]: The task, you know, the burden has been laid down.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it led him onwards until he reached the goal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Didn't he recognize suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00]: He recognized suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he thought he freed himself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, you can... and there were different dhammas, different teachings in the Buddha's day.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, well, not all of them are actually valid.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, they would not be leading you to the to the final goal of freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if your dhamma says, oh, understanding of this will free you from suffering, then you understand that, but you're not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's either the wrong dhamma or you haven't understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the faith in the Buddha's teaching has to come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you will have faith in a doctor when he prescribes your medicine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you don't have faith in the Buddha's teaching, if you were to start practicing, you're not free from suffering, but you understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think, okay, I understood this, but it's not freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll go to something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you have faith in the Buddha's teaching, then you'll question yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not going to place the blame on the teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll say, no, I have faith that this is right, yet I'm not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, I haven't fully understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you make more effort and more.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's a bit risky.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do pick up a wrong dhamma, a wrong teaching, a wrong instruction, even quoted as Buddhism, you'll end up wasting.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha says it was one of
[SPEAKER_01]: And certainly, in terms of demerit, it's presenting as dhamma that which is not dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, you can obstruct many beings in finding the true dhamma on account of something you just said.
[SPEAKER_01]: That kind of, you know, gain exposure and people heard it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, if you say...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of faith of the Buddha, they thought what you were saying was right.
[SPEAKER_01]: They followed it for 50 years, and they haven't... they're still puthujjana, and it's directly a result of what you basically misinterpret.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, that doesn't mean if you say something by accident, that somebody misunderstands.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, you deep down knowing you're puthujjana, and you go out and teach and tell people how to practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: It feels like, no, but I'm doing it out of good intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, good, misguided intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: And is that misguidedness?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's gonna cost you a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or could cost you a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it will affect others a lot more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And let alone if somebody intentionally, like fully, misrepresents.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you do hear it a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: A dhamma talk, where someone will talk and say, ends will start off.
[SPEAKER_00]: By saying...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know anything, but let me tell you how it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It absolves them a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they say, I don't know, I'm still a patujana, but I'll give you an hour-long dhamma talk, which is a contradiction in term.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't be a dhamma talk then, because talking about the dhamma is not a dhamma, but it's a different topic.
[SPEAKER_01]: It absolves them a bit, because then it's a responsibility on those listeners to then, hold on, he said he doesn't know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I mean, I might stay and listen, but I'll certainly not take any great heed in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if they ignore that and then carry on, it's a bit more than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But many people never, you know, they don't say that often enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't say often enough, hey, I don't know, but I'll talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll talk to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think they end up just getting used to talking and end up just talking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then people end up thinking, oh, they know what they're talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why a person who does want to learn and place faith, needs to be very careful where they place their faith in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you never compromise your intelligence, reasoning, discernment, even on account of faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you discern, you use what you... any tools you have, any grains of wisdom you have, you get them all together, and then choose wisely where you place your faith as something that's least likely going to be wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't know what's right, what's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is least likely to be mistaken down the road?
[SPEAKER_01]: And even there, you tread carefully, step by step.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, then, you know, if you did place it rightly or least wrongly, you will start to descend more and more, which means more and more grains of wisdom will be adding up, which means more and more of the right criteria will be shaping up, which means faster and faster you can go.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this... this is a strange one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ehipassika.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inviting everyone to come and see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or open to all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I think it's a bit illiberal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means come and see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Come and see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just come and see.
[SPEAKER_00]: A dharma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I want to really...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm interested in what you're teaching and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you really... Basically, the teaching pertains only to being done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I said, there is a difference between about the dhamma and the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And about the dhamma is not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a very important distinction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people who are about the dhamma, you tell them, no, come and see here, I do it, and that is what the dhamma is not what you...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're parroting the very same phrases and words, you're not actually trying to see it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's not the dhamma, it's about the dhamma, and that's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, come and see it, and then
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the only way to know it, is to come and see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh, hibāsiko.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, hibāsiko.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, saṃdhītika, meaning to feel visible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, come and see for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, come.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you do it, the more you see, the more you see, the more you can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if it's about the dhamma, it can often, like, have a... have a lid on it quite quickly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, okay, that's what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're not really making that personal effort, internally, to see it and understand it and free yourself from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It stops there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, dhamma is this, this and that, and I can talk about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can talk from different angles about it, but... it's kind of frozen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why it's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only dhamma, the real dhamma, is the dhamma that does... that
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's visible, they can be seen individually by the wise and those who make the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the concept...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Timeless.
[SPEAKER_01]: About timeless, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means it's simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't pertain to your past, your future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I don't want to say it's always in the present, because there's no choice about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But basically, timeless means it doesn't pertain to time, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the principles of dhamma are right there, present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your past is within those principles, your future is within those principles, and your present is already within those principles of the present dhamma, the universals of your experience, the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the thing that's saying, let be the past and the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll teach you the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because as we spoke before, your past is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your future is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can think about your past at any given time, and you're doing it in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can think ahead, plan your future,
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're thinking that, right there and then, in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can think about present things in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have past, present, future, and they're all within the domain of present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's no choice about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the Buddha talks about present, he talks about that general domain of present, in which past, future, and present are present.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't talk about that little present that's in between past and future, whereby don't think about the past, don't fantasize about the future, just be in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't help.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not really past-future-present.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's either past-present, present-future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, past-present or future-present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's over-determined and under-determined in regard to the determined, which is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: The linear of past, future, present, it's a fantasy.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're always like, in regard to present, things that were overly determined, things that were gone, things that were done, that's your past.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if you look at the other, the opposite way, in regard to this present, things that are yet to be, that's your future.
[SPEAKER_01]: But both are already within the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't stop thinking about the past or planning about the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you can do is, basically, not forget or not ignore that you're doing it presently.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you want to see the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that is already the principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And especially when it comes down to dhamma, as a teaching, if you talk about the principle of paticampāda, which is the timeless principle, principle of a kalika, that's a simultaneous presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with appearance, existence is.
[SPEAKER_01]: What we spoke before.
[SPEAKER_01]: But with craving, suffering is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneously present, to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now... and that is very important.
[SPEAKER_01]: To bring down and start discerning it together simultaneously to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you say suffering is because of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: People immediately assume, naturally assume, it's the craving that arises and then endures in time for a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: They say, oh, craving, I crave, I'm doing this, and then the suffering follows.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: May I just crave a little bit?
[SPEAKER_01]: The suffering is in the very presence of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could say it's the same thing, but it's not, because it can be discerned.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's certainly simultaneously present things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't possibly disjoin them and just say craving and look at the craving without suffering being present at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nor can you be thinking about suffering and discerning suffering without craving being present at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's timeless.
[SPEAKER_01]: And no matter how much time externally might be passing, notion of time might be passing, yesterday to today, this principle of simultaneous present is the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that general present which has past as over-determined and future as under-determined in regard to the determined.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but if you think that maybe it's craving and then suffering will arise in the future, there's maybe a possibility that it might not arise in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something else might arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, therefore, craving is not...
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, craving is not the timeless determination of the suffering, which is what the Tathāgata says it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: With craving, suffering is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might want to learn how to crave.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you recognize, okay, so it's the presence of craving, results in the presence of suffering, right there and then, to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the craving ceases, suffering cannot remain even for a nanosecond afterwards, without the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's simultaneously arising and simultaneously ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is the recognition of bodhichitta and pada.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, obviously, if you have the ultimate, the greatest wisdom of the Saṅgha, Sambuddha, then that one principle of simultaneous arising, simultaneous ceasing, you can sort of describe and define many, many, many different, well, twelve or more in Digha Nikaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you just start describing paticcaṁpāda in slightly different terms later on, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can go in all this intricately, but it's still the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why every paticcaṁpāda starts with this, this is, and then with what?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it goes on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why... and that... and... yeah, he did say, one who sees... no, Sariputra said, one who sees dhamma sees paticcaṁpāda, one who sees paticcaṁpāda sees the dhamma, because that
[SPEAKER_01]: Principle of simultaneous presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can... Again, you don't have to go into all of the intricate, very, very subtle descriptions of the Buddha and Bodhichitta Upādāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can just take the very coarse division of mind and body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because those are general phenomena, real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you start seeing your body as, well, inconceivable, without the presence of the mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: And vice versa.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind would be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you might... like... and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not thinking about it, by not discerning it as inconceivable, you end up conceiving it through your assumption that it might stay on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might.
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind might stay on when the body breaks apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: You conceive... many people conceive that through the assumption of it might.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you just said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't necessarily know, but just the fact that you don't see it simultaneously, you allow the possibility for it to enter, and that possibility is more than enough for the assumption of, yes, it will.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to think long enough, and you realize, well, whenever you think about your mind, there is an image of the body, at least in the background, or at least right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: If this body, physical body, is not operating, if this heart is not pumping, if this brain is not working,
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be able to think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because any experience of thinking that you know of, that you can think of, that you can imagine, even in the future, implies the notion of your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's inseparable from its saṅkhāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same again, if you were to start thinking about the body, you realize, well, I'm thinking about it, thus, I'm mentally accessing it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the only way you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no pure sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense in itself is not aware of itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But with the mind, there is sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: They meet in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They appear in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm beginning to see the extent of possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: So?
[SPEAKER_00]: To be able to see the extent of possibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean by that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, things can only go so far.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it can only go so... it can only be so far.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'm not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the mind is not...
[SPEAKER_00]: Not everything is possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't... it can't survive by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, OK. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK. That's what you mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't... by extent...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mean by the extent of all the possible... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, what you're saying is seeing the nature of possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you have to have a reasoned thing in order for possibilities to be possible in regard to what has a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, possibilities in themselves cannot exist.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot remain standing if there is not that which are possible... what they are possible in regard to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can assume the possibility that, you don't know, your mind might carry on, your consciousness might carry on itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you stop and think about it intelligently, authentically, recognize that any notion, any designation of your mind, of your consciousness, is known in this experience as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And here, when you think about the future, after your death, so to speak, you are assuming some sort of material body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is, like, not voluntarily, but it's implied in the notion of mind continuing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you only know mind as inseparable from, because it is inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, the question is basically just... sorry, no, the task is then to discern the notions of physical body that you carry in the assumptions of your mind in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the assumptions of the mind as free from body and everything else will just cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's inconceivable, even in theory, to just think about the mind without the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even that should affect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By that principle of being separable from.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you look at it closely, you'll see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you think my mind in the future, what you are there assuming most likely, most often, as your body, is basically your own face.
[SPEAKER_01]: Face of your own physical image.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you associate with that notion of mine, that it's now implied in that my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind, but at the very end of that image of my mind, there's a picture of pañña standing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you push it far enough, you'll see, oh, you apply, you imply your current form in that notion of my mind, because mind is inseparable from the form, even in theory.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or sense of mind, sense of form.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, that's the thing, that sense of mind or sense of form stands for that which form is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't actually have to have the physical physical, because even the physical physical is only a form of a sense of this current present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Currently, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I said, if you try and think about your body right here, right now, look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know it, and aspects of it, because they appear mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: These images appear mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus form rūpa in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can see it through the assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the nature of seeing assets.
[SPEAKER_00]: How it is simultaneously risen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneously risen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, as I said, you don't have to... you don't have to go into intricate details of this and that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just discover the principle where this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then drill everything through that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your gateway, that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of the mind, presence of... Look, two separate domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: They exist... You don't want to say co-exist or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: They appear simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they're, like, impossible to discern one apart from the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So even when you're just thinking abstractly about one, the other one is implying that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can come down even slightly coarser, and you can even say, well, would you be able to think about a future and your mind carrying on, if this body is not living right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to have those thoughts that pertain to the future, if this body is not breathing right there, while you're thinking it?
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter how separate, how different it feels, it arranges together.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's hard to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it only pertains to the simple nature of simultaneous presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else in common.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's so easy to assume that there are, mind and body, they might... they're two different entities.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're two separate entities.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're like, you know, they might sort of... one is left, the other one is right.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might do things together or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's hard to just see, to discern, that the only thing they really have in common is that they're simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't see one without the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you build on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because no matter how pleasing your fantasy about, you know, well, my mind, my consciousness will continue because it makes sense, because of this, because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're thinking those very things right there, right now, in that very present moment, while your body is breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Their body, their heart stops at the time, right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to continue those thoughts?
[SPEAKER_01]: When the only thoughts you know so far, and the thoughts that you're trying to send into future as valid facts, are known because of the breathing body right here or now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you actually have no concept of what experience of mind without a living body would be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even when you think about the possibility of it, that already implies that body living, because you're thinking about the possibility of it while you're living.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unfortunately, you don't need to.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you have to do is stop assuming it.
[SPEAKER_01]: See one depending on the other and you, your sense of self, is completely redundant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because it's redundant, it will fade by itself through the cultivation of this simultaneous... through this principle of simultaneity.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's important.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you don't have to see your mind as inseparable from the body and the body as indistinguishable without the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to see that first and then free yourself from the self-view and I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Freedom from those things will be the result of seeing that principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the body is there given a reason and the mind in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no room for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by knowing that there can't be any sense of self in regard to those things, because they... they're indifferent to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just mind and body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two sticks holding each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remove one, the other one goes with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not knowing that you can't own those things, can't control, can't be in them, you place yourself in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You assume.
[SPEAKER_01]: You assume you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: By fully discerning that you can't be there, you stop assuming that you are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now you know that you can't be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this mind, right here, right there, and this body, right here, right there, whatever, for you, yours, for me, mine, is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can have all the, you know, on a more particular level, all the experiences of this sense or that sense, this emotion or that emotion, this aggregate or that aggregate, depending on the approach you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: But basically, you do need all the living body and the consciousness in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those two things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they're inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't uproot your consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you can do is remove desire and lust in regard to them, and then there won't be any problems.
[SPEAKER_01]: Desire and lust that manifests through basically lust or aversion or delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard to that inaccessible, in regard to the principle of those inaccessible things, matter and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when I say inaccessible, I mean, by that I mean you can't take all of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't, I mean, you can't even think consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You certainly can't think pure form, because you can see a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking pure form, thus, that's a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not pure form.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even the idea of something being a pure form can only be known as a thought of that which pure form might be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's a thought in its nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can I know pure form?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can just remove its footing, its appropriation, so it can't touch you and you're done.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha says he trains himself thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just training, repeating.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what training is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Repetition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just repeating, training, and training, and increasing, and training, and so on.